<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <front>
        <docTitle>
           <titlePart type="main">excerpt from LIFE OF SAMUEL RICHARDSON, WITH REMARKS ON HIS WRITINGS.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor>Anna Letitia Barbauld</docAuthor>
     </front>
      <body>
         <p>The author of Clarissa was always fond of female society. He lived in a kind of flower-garden of ladies: they were his inspirers, his critics, his applauders. Connections of business apart, they were his chief correspondents. He had generally a number of young ladies at his house, whom he used to engage in conversation on some subject of sentiment, and provoke, by artful opposition, to display the treasures of intellect they possessed. Miss Mulso, afterwards Mrs. Chapone; Miss Highmore, now Mrs. Duncombe; Miss Talbot, niece to Secker, and author of some much esteemed devotional pieces; Miss Prescott, afterwards Mrs. Mulso; Miss Fieldings; and Miss Colliers, resided occasionally with him. He was accustomed to give the young ladies he esteemed the endearing appellation of his daughters. He used to write in a little summer-house, or grotto<!--*[2]-->, as it was called, within his garden, before the family were up; and, when they met at breakfast, he communicated the progress of his story, which, by that means, had every day a fresh and lively interest. Then began the criticisms, the pleadings, for Harriet Byron or Clementina; every turn and every incident was eagerly canvassed, and the author enjoyed the benefit of knowing before-hand how his situations would strike. Their own little partialities and entanglements, too, were developed, and became the subject of grave advice, or lively raillery. Mrs. Duncombe thus mentions the agreeable scene, in a letter to Mrs. Mulso.</p>
         <p><!--How do I handle this letter?-->
            I shall often, in idea, enjoy again the hours that we have so agreeably spent in the delightful retirement of North End:
            <lg>
               <l>For while this pleasing subject I pursue,</l> 
               <l>The grot, the garden, rush upon my view; </l> 
               <l>There, in blest union, round the friendly gate,</l> 
               <l>Instruction, Peace, and chearful Freedom wait;</l> 
               <l>And there, a choir of list'ning nymphs appears</l> 
               <l>Oppress'd with wonder, or dissolved in tears;</l>
               <l>But on her tender fears when Harriet dwells,</l> 
               <l>And love's soft symptoms innocently tells,</l>
               <l>They all, with conscious smiles, those symptoms view,</l> 
               <l>And by those conscious smiles confess them true.</l>
            </lg><!--end of letter--> </p>
         <p>Mr. Richardson was a friend to mental improvement in women, though under all those restrictions which modesty and decorum have imposed upon the sex. Indeed, his sentiments seem to have been more favourable to female literature, before than after his intercourse with the fashionable world; for Clarissa has been taught Latin, but Miss Byron is made to say, that she does not even know which are meant by the learned languages, and to declare, that a woman who knows them is an owl among the birds. The prejudice against any appearance of extraordinary cultivation in women, was, at that period, very strong. It will scarcely be believed, by this generation, that Mrs. Delany, the accomplished Mrs. Delany, objects to the words intellect and ethics, in one of the conversation pieces, in Grandison, as too scholastic to proceed from the mouth of a female. What would some of these critics have said, could they have heard young ladies talking of gases, and nitrous oxyd, and stimuli, and excitability, and all the terms of modern science. The restraint of former times was painful and humiliating; what can be more humiliating than the necessity of affecting ignorance? and yet, perhaps, it is not undesirable that female genius should have something to overcome; so much, as to render it probable, before a woman steps out of the common walks of life, that her acquirements are solid, and her love for literature decided and irresistible. These obstacles did not prevent the Epictetus of Mrs. Carter, nor the volumes of Mrs. Chapone, from being written and given to the world.</p>
         <p>The moral qualities of Richardson were crowned with a serious and warm regard for religion; it is conspicuous in all his works; and we shall, probably, not find any writings, of the class of novels, in which virtue and piety are so strongly and uniformly recommended, without any party spirit, or view to recommend a particular system, and it would be doing injustice to the taste of the world not to say that they were highly valued on that account. The house of Richardson was a school of virtuous sentiment and good morals. The following letter, from Mr. Reich, of Leipsic, shews the pleasing impression a visit to him made on the lively feelings of a foreigner.</p>
         <p> You know, Sir, I set out for England purely with a view of cultivating a personal acquaintance with so great a man as Mr. Samuel Richardson, who had so long endeared himself to me by his works, and who, afterwards, by the correspondence established between us, granted me his friendship. I arrived at London the eighth of August, and had not much difficulty in finding Mr. Richardson in this great city. He gave me a reception worthy of the author of Pamela, Clarissa, and Grandison; that is, with the same heart which appears throughout his works. His person, his family, and even his domestics, all answer this character. He carried me into his library, and his printing-house, (for he is a printer), in both which I never saw things so well disposed. Sunday following, I was with him at his country-house, (Selby-house) where his family was, with some ladies, acquaintances of his four daughters, who, with his lady, compose his family. It was there I saw beauties without affectation; wit without vanity; and thought myself transported to an inchanted land. After chocolate, Mr. Richardson brought  us into the garden, adjoining to the house. He invited me to partake of its fruits, of which the trees afforded the finest of their kind; and, perceiving that I hesitated, gathered some himself, which he presented to me. Every thing I saw, every thing I tasted, recalled to me the idea of the golden age. Here are to be seen no counterfeits, such as are the offspring of vanity, and the delight of fools. A noble simplicity reigns throughout, and elevates the soul. The harmony of this charming family furnished me with many reflections on the common ill-judged methods of education, whence springs the source either of our happiness or misery. The ladies affected not that stiff preciseness peculiar to coquettes. Trained up by a parent who instructs them, still more by his example than by his works, they strive to imitate him; and, if you feel a tenderness for objects so lovely, you will surely be sensible of a still greater respect for them.</p>
         <p>In the middle of the garden, over against the house, we came to a kind of grotto, where we rested ourselves. It was on this seat, Mr. Le Fevre, (Mr. Richardson's friend) told me, that Pamela, Clarissa, and Grandison, received their birth; I kissed the ink-horn on the side of it. We afterwards proceeded to table, (dinner,) where an opportunity was offered me of reading the letters written to me by Malle. Sack, from Berlin, concerning my voyage, and Mr. Richardson. One might in them discern that wit which is the peculiar characteristic of that lady; and, every one listened with the closest attention to whatever truth obliged me to say concerning her. Whereupon Mr. Richardson observed to me, that the ladies in company were all his adopted daughters: that he should be very proudto give to them, as well as to his own, so charming a sister; and desired to signify as much to her, and to send her his picture, which he gave me for that purpose. The rest of our discourse turned on the merits of Mr. Gellert, and of some other Germans of distinction. I told him, we had the same reason to glory in our relationship, as countrymen of these worthy gentlemen, as the English had in regard to him. Mr. Richardson's usual modesty dictated his answer. Towards evening he brought me to London, where he made me promise to come and see him as often as I could. On the Sunday following I was with him again at his pleasant country seat. We found there a large company, all people of merit; Mr. Miller, author of the Gardener's Dictionary, (which has been translated at Nurnburg, with such success), and Mr. Highmore, the famous painter, were there. This last, two days afterwards, conferred on me a genteel piece of civility, which I shall never forget: he must, indeed, be the accomplished gentleman he appears to be, by obliging with so good a grace. I was extremely concerned on not seeing his only daughter, who was in the country. I have read some of her letters, which excite in me the highest esteem both for her understanding and her heart. In the evening I took my leave of the family, and returned with Mr. Richardson. I saw him several times since, during the eight days I staid in England; but it was necessary, at last, to quit that divine man. I gave him the letter entitled No. I. he embraced me, and a mutual tenderness deprived us of speech. He accompanied me with his eyes as far as he could: I shed tears.</p>
         <p>There is one fault of which it will not be easy to clear our author. It is said that he was vain; he was fed with praise, and, with regard to that diet, it may be truly affirmed, that 
            <!--Hamletincrease of appetite doth grow  
            By what it feeds on. [3]-->
         </p>
         <p>In the circle of his admirers, his own works occupied, naturally, a large share of conversation; and he had not the will, nor perhaps the variety of knowledge necessary to turn it on other topics. The same subject forms the prominent feature in his correspondencies.—Impartiality, perhaps, requires a biographer to notice the opinion of such a man as Johnson, delivered through the medium of Mr. Boswell's memory, as follows, giving an account of a conversation at Mr. Nairne's, where Dr. Johnson drew the character of Richardson. "I only remember that he expressed a high value for his talents and virtues: But that his perpetual study was to ward off petty inconveniences, and to procure petty pleasures; that his love of continual superiority was such, that he took care always to be surrounded by women, who listened to him implicitly, and did not venture to contradict his opinions; and that his desire of distinction was so great, that he used to give large vails to Speaker Onslow's servants, that they might treat him with respect." [4]</p>
         <p>It may be observed upon this, that the ladies he associated with were well able to appreciate his works. They were both his critics and his models, and from their sprightly conversation, and the disquisitions on love and sentiment, which took place, he gathered what was more to his purpose than graver topics would have produced. He was not writing a dictionary, like Johnson, or a history, like Gibbon. He was a novel writer; his business was not only with the human heart, but with the female heart.</p>
         <!--Astrisk note *The same of which an engraving is given in the work.-->
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
