<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--<?xml-model href="Schematron_HIST630_Final.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->


<?xml-model href="out/LeutesdorfForestODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="out/LeutesdorfForestODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Leutesdorf Forest Investigation</title>
            <author>Captain Richard W. Secor</author>
            <respStmt><resp>Editor</resp><name>Tristan Krause</name></respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded for DHUM 630 Spring 2023</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Narrative on Investigation of Cases in the Leutesdorf Forest, November 26, 1947, Arolsen Archives 2.1.3.1/70818647-652</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front><docAuthor>Captain Richard W. Secor</docAuthor><docTitle><titlePart type="main">NARRATIVE ON INVESTIGATION OF CASES IN THE <placeName ref="#place002">LEUTESDORFER FOREST</placeName></titlePart><titlePart type="sub">COORDINATES:(K-5i/F-70),<placeName ref="#place001">Germany</placeName></titlePart>
      </docTitle></front>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" /><label n="261"></label><label><stamp>ITS 024</stamp></label> <label> (Germany K-5I) 9786</label>
<!--RWWS/hb. 
26 November 1947-->
         <div type="report">
         <p>An "on the spot" investigation of <placeName ref="#place002">LEUTESDORF FOREST</placeName> revealed the wreckage of a B-I7 SN.43-38189, nicknamed "Powerful Katinka." Missing Air Crew Heport #K-484 shows nine (9) members of the crew in plane at the time of crash, four (4) returned to Military Control, five (5) on a PDD Status. Inclosed for reference are two Missing Air Crew Reports (#K-484 Exhibit "A" and #R-348 Exhibit "B").</p>
            <p><persName ref="#person001">DRUGAN, DONALD T.</persName>, 2nd It., 0-768485. Burial Report shows <persName ref="#person001">Lt. DHUGAN</persName> as being disinterred with two (2) I.D. tags from <placeName ref="#place003">BEROD</placeName> (K-5L/wP-9727), <placeName ref="#place001">Germany</placeName> end coming from plane, identified by two machine gun numbers 647650 and 647764 (MACR # H-348), of which <persName ref="#person001">Lt. DRUGAN</persName> was not a member. This B-IT7 SN. 42-31582 is believed to have crashed in the vicinity of <placeName ref="#place003">BEROD</placeName>, <placeName ref="#place001">Germany</placeName>.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#person002">MOHN, JONATHAN V.</persName>, 2nd Lt., 0-775481. Burial Report shows <persName ref="#person002">Lt. MOHN</persName> disinterred from <placeName ref="#place002">LEUTESDORF FOREST</placeName> (K-51/F-7506), <placeName ref="#place001">Germany</placeName> as a surface burial, identified by two (2)I.D. tags. No. K-484 <persName ref="#person002">Lt. MOHN</persName> is listed as Co-pilot.</p>
            <!--<note type="" resp="#unknown">Amerika</note>-->
            <p><persName ref="#person003">WASSERMANN, GERALD M.</persName>, 2nd Lt., 0-2060421. As far as records show <persName ref="#person003">Lt. WASSEHMANN</persName> is not re-interred as a known. (See Exhibit "C"). Forester <persName ref="#person012">WALSDORF </persName>located the remains of <persName ref="#person003">WASSERMANN</persName> (NARRATIVE on Investigation of Cases in the <placeName ref="#place002">LEUTESDORF FOREST</placeName>, dtd. 26 November 1947, cont'd.)</p>         
          <!--Amerika-->
         <pb n="2" /><label n="262"></label><label><stamp>ITS 025</stamp></label>
            <p>and removed the I.D. tag. The remains were interred in <placeName ref="#place004">Leutesdorf</placeName> Cemetery and since disinterred by an unknown <!--American--> Unit. Mr. <persName ref="#person012">WALSDORF</persName> gave the I.D. tag to the <!--Undersigned-->. All the people that had anything to do with handling the remains were questioned in an attempt to definitely establish the grave <persName ref="#person003">WASSERMANN</persName> was buried in <placeName ref="#place004">Leutesdorf</placeName> Cemetery so final identification could be made, but nothing could be obtained.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#person004">PARKER, JURL T.</persName>, Sgt. 38469636. Records of this Headquarters show <persName ref="#person004">Sgt. PARKER</persName>disinterred as Unknown X-2278, later identified. X-2278 was disinterred from <placeName ref="#place003">BEROD</placeName>,(K-5I/xF-9727), <placeName ref="#place001">Germany</placeName>. On the back of the burial report <persName ref="#person004">Sgt. PARKER</persName> came from the B-I7 with machine gun numbers 647650 and 647764 which is not the plane <persName ref="#person004">Sgt. PARKER</persName> was in</p>
            <p><persName ref="#person005">STEVENS, ROBERT</persName>, Sgt., 39719976. There is no record of Sgt.<persName ref="#person004">Stevens</persName> being re-interred as a known. Forester <persName ref="#person012">WALSDORF</persName> was present at the time the remains were located and interred in <placeName ref="#place004">LEUTESDORF</placeName> Cemetery and since disinterred by an unknown <!--American--> Unit. (Exhibit "D").From the above information it appears the remains from the two planes were mixed up after disinterment. A total of fifteen (15) remains were disinterred from <placeName ref="#place004">LEUTESDORF</placeName> Cemetery and adjacent woods, fourteen (14) from the cemetery and one (I) from the woods <persName ref="#person001">(Lt. MOHN)</persName>. Of the fifteen (15) deceased five (5) described above were from B-I7 reported on MACR #K-484, and ten (10) were from B-I7 reported on MACR #V-43. (Exhibit “E”).</p></div>
         <div type="report">
         <!--Narrative on Investigation of Cases in the Leutesdorf Forest. dtd. 26 November 1947, cont'd.)-->
            <p>With reference to Begic Communications, Cese Numbers (Germany K-5I) 9786 and 9808, pertaining to several <!--American--> graves in the <placeName ref="#place002">FOREST OF LEUTESDORF</placeName>, negative results were obtained. Mr. <persName ref="#person020">KROHN</persName> was contacted and his information came from several other people, primarily Mr. <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="#person021">ULMERSBACH</persName>.</p>
         <pb n="3" /><label n="263"></label><label><stamp>ITS 026</stamp></label>
            <p>Mr. <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> was contacted with reference to inclosures signed by SS Troops, he has a very revengeful attitude and has the tendency to exaggerate. Mr. <persName ref="#person021">ULMERSBACH</persName> was also contacted end his attitude is much the same as Mr. <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName>, because the Americans upon taking <placeName ref="#place004">Leutesdorf</placeName> put him in as Burgermeister, later the <!--German--> people through the <!--French--> had him thrown out. The French War Crimes Commission at <placeName ref="#place005">KOBLENZ</placeName> worked with the undersigned and carried out an investigation of their own, resulting in Mr. <persName ref="#person011">GROMIG's</persName> arrest and eventual trial. Inclosed as Exhibit "F" is the capy of the <!--French--> investigation.</p>
            <div type="list"><head>The <!--undersigned -->obtained statements from the following people:</head>
         <list>
            <item>Exhibit "G" Statement of Mr. <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName></item>
            <item>Exhibit "H" Statement of the boy <persName ref="#person010">SCHUTZ</persName> who originally was too young to legally sign his name, but signed the statement later upon the request of the undersigned.</item>
            <item>Exhibit "I" and “J" Statement of Nr. <persName ref="#person011">GROMIG</persName></item>
            <item>Exhibit "K" Statement of Mr. <persName ref="#person012">WALSDORF</persName></item>
            <item>Exhibit "L" Statement of Mr. <persName ref="#person013">GLUSING</persName></item></list></div>
            <div type="report">
               <p>Included in the <!--French--> Investigation("Exhibit "F") are statements from Mr. <persName ref="#person013">GLUSING</persName>, Mrs. <persName ref="#person015">ZUES</persName>, Mis <persName ref="#person024">BARKLAGE</persName>, Mr. <persName ref="#person011">GROMIG</persName>, Mr. <persName ref="#person015">ZUES</persName>, Mr. <persName ref="#person017">WIMBRSBACH</persName>, Mr. <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> and Mr. <persName ref="#person012">WALSDORF</persName>. Additional information was obtained from Mr. <persName ref="#person018">SCHNEIDER</persName> (Exhibit "M") and Mr. <persName ref="#person013">GLUSING</persName> (Exhibit "N"). A sketch is attached as exhibit "O". Following is a summary of the information obtained: A four (4) motored Bomber supposedly crashed in the vicinity of <placeName ref="#place004">Leutesdorf</placeName>. Several planes crashed in this area and have been located, identified and crews accounted for. The Bomber in question can not be located, identified, or any members of its crew identified. At the time of the crash which took place about September or October 1944, one (I) crew-member lived in the <placeName ref="#place002">LEUTESDORF</placeName> Woods for three(3) or four (4) weeks. During this time he made and lived in two huts (2), located</p>
         <pb n="4" /><label n="264"></label><label><stamp>ITS 027</stamp></label>
               <p>as shown on Exhibit "O" at points B and C. In the month of October 1944, the forester<persName ref="#person012">WALSDORF</persName>found this airmen at point C. took him to a farm (Point D), where he talked to two <!--French--> POWs and ate a meal. (Exhibits "P" end ""). From one POW a description of the <!--airmen--> was obtained : Forty (40) years to forty-five years old, radio operator from a four (4) motored Bomber with a crew of mostly negros, height about one (I) meter and seventy-five (75) cm, heavily built, about eighty (80) kgs, black heir, dark skin, small eyes, married to an Americen nurse stationed in <placeName ref="#place006">Paris</placeName> and had two children.</p>
               <p>From point D the airmen was taken to the Burgermeister's OFFICE in <placeName ref="#place004">Leutesdorf</placeName>, registered (Records have since been lost), And evacuated at <placeName ref="#place007">Neuwied</placeName>. One or two days later, the prisoner was returned to LEUTESDORF, in the company of a member of the GESTAPO named <persName ref="#person019">EICH</persName> (<persName ref="#person019">EICH</persName> wes killed toward the end of the war by <!--German--> soldiers,) and a member of the <!--French--> Legion. From the Burgermeister's Office they proceeded to <placeName ref="#place008">HUBERTUSHOF</placeName> with <persName ref="#person011">GROMIG</persName>. At <placeName ref="#place008">HUBERTUSHOF</placeName> the Forester wes not there to show the way into the woods, so a boy named <persName ref="#person010">SCHUTZ</persName> proceeded to direct the group, which by this time had increased in number to five (5). From <placeName ref="#place008">HUBERTUSHOF</placeName> they followed the route indicated by a red pencil on the sketch Exhibit "I".</p>
         <p>From this point on there are several stories, but this is what the undersigned believed happened:</p>
         <p>The group of five (5) proceeded to a point in the woods, indicated at Point E, where Mr. <persName ref="#person011">GROMIG</persName> told the boy <persName ref="#person010">SCHUTZ</persName> to return. The boy departed in the direction indicated by a blue pencil and returned to <placeName ref="#place004">Leutesdorf</placeName>. For the first 100 hundred yards after the boy departed, he looked back and watched the remaining four (4) enter the woods at Point F. Information as to what happened from there on is very vague. It is further believed, however, <persName ref="#person011">GROMIG</persName>, <persName ref="#person019">EICH</persName>, the <!--French--> Legionnaire and the airmen proceeded into the woods and the airmen shot at a point unknown. Since <persName ref="#person019">EICH</persName> is dead, the <!--French--> Legionnaire is Unknown and <persName ref="#person011">GROMIG</persName> will not talk, it is very difficult to locate the place of murder. The party without the <!--airman--> returned to <placeName ref="#place004">Leutesdorf</placeName>, where various converstions</p>
         <pb n="5" /><label n="265"></label><label><stamp>ITS 028</stamp></label>
         <p>were held and remarks made. The LEUTESDORF woods have been thoroughly searched along the routes followed and at Points B,E,F and C with negative results as to locating the grave. It is believed at this time as every possible clue has been followed up and no further information is available.</p>
         <p>Another grave referred to in the basic communication was reported by Mr. <persName ref="#person018">SCHNEIDER</persName>. While walking in the woods one day with his two boys in May 1944, <persName ref="#person018">SCHNEIDER</persName> found a body.(Exhibits "G" and "M”). The <!--undersigned--> took Mr.<persName ref="#person018">SCHNEIDER</persName> into the woods to have him point out the spot where he had seen the body, indicated on the sketch at Point A. After searching the ground in the vicinity of Point A, a soft spot was found and the remains of a body were discovered. The deceased was clothed, as Mr. <persName ref="#person018">SCHNEIDER</persName> stated, as follows: Civilian Clothes and parts of a <!--French--> uniform, <!--French--> shoes, <!--French--> aspirin tube in the pocket. The head was in several pieces end a piece of denture was found, part of a plate from a full set of false teeth. Printed on the rubber part of the plate was MEUNIER BURDIN PATENT NO. 00. From all appearances the remains are not <!--American--> or English, but are <!--French-->.</p>
               <p>In Exhibit “C" the statement <persName ref="#person013">GLUSING</persName> made, according to <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName>, was "keep mum about this, it was not only one (I) but three (3), they were spies", is a false statement made by <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> to implicate more people. Another Letter from <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> mentioned in basic communication refers to a wounded pilot. All of the information <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> has written is second or third hand and exaggerated. The wounded pilot was taken to a hospital and has been returned to the Z.I. His name was <persName ref="#person022">SMITH Paul E.</persName>, PFC. 13155431, reported on MARC #K-503. Exhibit "R". Two (2) other remains referred to by Mr. <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> have been disinterred and reburied in <placeName ref="#place009">HAMM</placeName>, Military Cemetery. They are: <persName ref="#person006">CHINCHILLA, FRANCIS P.</persName> and <persName ref="#person007">HOLLENBECK, CHARLES E.</persName>(Exhibit "R") who were murdered and buried in <placeName ref="#place010">WOLLENDORF</placeName>. Since disinterment, persons concerned with the atrocity have been tried and punished.</p>
         <pb n="6" /><label n="266"></label><label><stamp>ITS 029</stamp></label>
         <p>With reference to letter from Office of Military Government, Liaison and Security
            Office, SK, LK, <placeName ref="#place011">Offenbach</placeName> <placeName ref="#place012">(Hessen)</placeName> APO 633, US.Army, signed by <persName ref="#person023">Arthur SHANLY</persName>, 1st LT., Mr. <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> is not working for the <!--French--> Military Government. The reason the <!--French--> told him to keep quiet is because <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> has been living in this vicinity which has been about all his life. He has been arrested fourteen (14) times for stirring up trouble. Mr. <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> can only refer to other people as he has no first hand information.It has been rumored by <persName ref="#person009">LINZ</persName> that Frau <persName ref="#person015">ZUES</persName> gave the <!--French--> wine to have Mr. <persName ref="#person014">ZUES</persName> released from jail. This rumor is also false. The <!--French--> buy wine from all the wine merchants in the <!--French--> Zone. The <!--French--> War Crimes Commission in <placeName ref="#place005">KOBLENZ</placeName> and the <!--French--> Military Government in <placeName ref="#place005">KOBLENZ</placeName> and <placeName ref="#place007">NEUWIED</placeName> have been working in conjunction with the <!--undersigned--> and have been of great help and assistance.</p>
         <!--CONCLUSION : -->
         <p>That all the deceased mentioned in the Basic Communications (Germany K-5I) 9786 and 9808 have been recovered except of one (I) unknown airmen, murdered in the LEUTESDORF FOREST.All possible efforts have been exhausted with negative results as to the location of an
            <!--American--> grave.</p>
               <p>signed <persName ref="#person008">Richard W. Secor</persName> 
            Capt. Inf. 
            164th Q. BN. AGRC 
            Investigator. -->
            Copy of 2.1.3.1 / 70818652</p></div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
